<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A description of the prophets, apostles, and ministers of Christ, and also of those called ministers of England, by men which say they are ministers of Christ, but are found to be blasphemers and lyars, and none of the ministers of Christ Iesus; and wherein the difference plainly appears, and they made manifest. With an exhortation to the people of England; to forsake them, their blind-guides, and to follow Christ Iesus, the shepard of their souls; the way, the truth, and life, who faith, come learn of me, for I am meek and lowly, ... / Given forth to undeceive the simple hearted; by him whose name in the flesh, is, Henry Clark.</title>
            <author>Clark, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E861_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206653</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865769</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865769</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 130:E861[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A description of the prophets, apostles, and ministers of Christ, and also of those called ministers of England, by men which say they are ministers of Christ, but are found to be blasphemers and lyars, and none of the ministers of Christ Iesus; and wherein the difference plainly appears, and they made manifest. With an exhortation to the people of England; to forsake them, their blind-guides, and to follow Christ Iesus, the shepard of their souls; the way, the truth, and life, who faith, come learn of me, for I am meek and lowly, ... / Given forth to undeceive the simple hearted; by him whose name in the flesh, is, Henry Clark.</title>
                  <author>Clark, Henry, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at his shop, at the Black-spread-Eagle neer the west end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 7th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Blasphemy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Priesthood --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118020:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DESCRIPTION OF The <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> OF CHRIST, And Alſo Of thoſe called Miniſters of England, by men which ſay they are Miniſters of CHRIST, but are found to be Blaſphemers and Lyars, and none of the Miniſters of Chriſt Ieſus; and wherein the difference plainly appears, and they made manifeſt.</p>
            <p>With an Exhortation to the People of England; to forſake them, their Blind-Guides, and to follow Chriſt Ieſus, the Shephard of their Souls; the Way, the Truth, and Life, who ſaith, come learn of me, for I am meek and lowly,
<q>
                  <p>My Sheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow me: And the good Shepheard goeth before his Sheep, and they follow him, for they know his voice; and a ſtranger they will not follow, but will flye from him, for they own not the voice of ſtrangers: <bibl>
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> the 10. chap.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <p>Work out your ſalvation with fear and trembling, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. Thus ſaith the Lord, what Houſe will ye build me? and where is the place of my reſt? but to this man will I look, even to him that is poor, and of a contrite ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and trembleth at my word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.1, 2. And dwell with him that is of an humble and contrite ſpirit, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. Fear ye not me, ſaith the Lord? will ye not tremble at my preſence? but this people hath a revolting and a rebellious heart, they are revolted and gone; neither ſay they in their hearts, let us fear the Lord our God, <bibl>
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.22, 23, 24.</bibl>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Given forth to undeceive the ſimple hearted; by him whoſe Name in the Fleſh is,</hi> HENRY CLARK.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for</hi> Giles Calvert, <hi>and are to be ſold at his ſhop,</hi> at the Black-ſpread-Eagle neer the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1655.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118020:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118020:2"/>
            <head>A Deſcription of the <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prophets, Apoſtles, and Miniſters of Chriſt are called and choſen and approved out of God, ſent out of their own countreyes, their fathers houſe and kindred, into all Countreys and Cities to declare the meſſage of their Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But thoſe called Miniſters and Teachers in England, they are onely choſen and approved off by men, and not called of God; ſo that they are no Miniſters of Chriſt, but are mens Miniſters, ſent forth by men into a particular Pariſh to preach; but the ſheep of Chriſt them they follow not, nor their voice do they own, becauſe they are ſtrangers and aliens from the life and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles and Miniſters of Chriſt forſake Father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Brethren and ſiſters, Wife and children, Houſe and lands, Trades or occupations, honors and pleaſures, and delights; deny themſelves of all, and take up their croſs daily, and follow Chriſt Jeſus whetherſoever he goes, and goes where he ſends them, as lambs amongſt wolves.</p>
            <p>Thoſe called Miniſters of England, have not forſaken nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied themſelves of any thing, but injoy all things, as Father &amp; Mother, Brethren and Siſters, Wife and children, houſe and land, honors, profits, pleaſures and delights, tythes and money, for which they preach in the Pariſh where they are ſetled by men, and ſtay, being not ſent thither of God; ſo that Chriſt they follow not, but are ſuch who minde earthly things, whoſe God is their belly, whoſe glory is in their ſhame, and are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118020:3"/> to the croſs of Chriſt, whoſe end is deſtruction, and therefore are no Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles, and Miniſters of Chriſt, have a diſpenſation of the Goſpel committed to them, and a command from the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to go into all countries, or nations, to preach the Goſpel in every creature, and wo unto them if they preach not that Goſpel; which command they obey, and go out into all countries, and provide neither gold nor ſilver in their purſe, nor two coats, neither ſhooes, nor ſcrip for their jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, neither ſtaff in their hands, neither are they to ſtay in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh to take tythes, gifts, nor rewards, but to go from city to city, and from one town to another, and as they have freely received, ſo freely give, without taking thought for the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, what they ſhall eat or what they ſhall drink, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they ſhall be cloathed, but caſt their care upon him, who taketh care and provideth things convenient for them, without taking tythes, gifts or rewards.</p>
            <p>Thoſe called Miniſters of England have no diſpenſation of the Goſpel committed to them by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they by the Lord of the Harveſt, ſent to labour in his Vineyard, neither in it do they labour, but are ſent by men to preach in a pariſhes high place, where they being ſetled, have for their preaching, ſome 40, 50, 60, 80: or 100. l. a year, which they know of before they will be ſetled there, which is in tythes, gifts, and rewards, to cloath themſelves in long Robes, and rich Black Attire, and their Wives in Silk, Gold and Silver Lace, Rings, and coſtly Raiment, with changeable ſuits of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell; and yet with this they are not contented, but ſeek for gain from their Quarters, and if they can hear of a Pariſh, whoſe Miniſter is dead, or turned out of his place, and if there be but 10, 20, or 30. l. a year more than he had from the people of the pariſh where he is, if all the means and friends he can make, can and wil help him into it, that for his preaching he may get more money, which is the Root of all evill; he will leave his Flock, and like a Hireling flye away, becauſe he is an Hireling, to the other, where none purſues him, or elſe will ſeek a Lecturers place, as they call it, in another pariſh, where he may have 20.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118020:3"/> or 30. l. a year more, and no further will they go to preach, than for their own advantage, as witneſs their Funerall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, ſo called, that when a Rich man or woman is dead, and to be buryed, for 10. s. 13. s. 4: d. or 20. s. they will preach a Sermon; but if a poor man or woman dye, that hath not 10. s: to give them, they will not preach nor give them praiſe as they do the rich for their money, when they are dead; therefore it doth plainly appear they are none of the Miniſters of <hi>Christ,</hi> but ſuch as go when they are not ſent, and come when they are not called of God, and cloathe themſelves with the fleece, and feed themſelves with the fat, and take no care for their Flock, but for their gain; and ſuch the true Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt were, and are, ſent to cry wo againſt.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters, Prophets, and Apoſtles of Chriſt, they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred about in ſheep-skins, and Goat-skins, in Deſarts, and Mountains, and lad in dens and caves of the earth, and had no certain dwelling place on the earth, being deſtitute, affl cted, tormented, and ſuffered cruell mockings, ſtripes, and impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, having their Legs put in the Stocks, yet were no Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, Vagrants, nor Wandring diſorderly idle perſons, but Fellow-labourers in the Goſpel, whoſe habitation is with God, and for his ſake, who loves them with an everlaſting love, and for the peoples ſakes, wom they are contented to ſpend and be ſpent; for the gaining of their ſouls to life, do they ſuffer all things.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Ministers</hi> of England, and <hi>Preachers,</hi> ſo called, they ſet themſelves down in a <hi>Pariſh,</hi> in one of the beſt livings, and faireſt houſes therein, or it will not ſerve their turn, but til they can get a better, or more money, and never go abroad into all Nations, but live at their homes at eaſe with their wives and children, and friends, eating and drinking of the beſt of the land, and of the fineſt of the Wheat, and are merry, taking their pleaſures, receiving their profits, Gifts and Rewards, Tythes, &amp; Eeaſter Reckonings, which comes unto them by the ſweate of other mens Browes, themſelves fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling no Sorrow, nor being in Trouble, as other men,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118020:4"/> being invited to Feaſts, ſet uppermoſt in the room, and are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of men Maſter, ſtand praying in Satans Synagogue, and for a pretence make long prayer, to be ſeen of men, and think to be heard for their much babbling; but the prayers of the wicked are abomination to the Lord, and he wil not hear their prayers, becauſe their hands are ful of blood, who murder by conſent, for thoſe that put into their mouths they cry peace to, let them be what they will, but thoſe that do not bring unto them, and put in their mouths, they prepare war againſt, by ſuing men at Law for tythes, and making diſtreſs upon their goods for tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble damages, or impriſoning their bodies, to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> undoing of them, their wives and families, which the Apoſtles and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt never did, nor had any command ſo to do, and where the life and power of Godlineſs appears in any to their faces, they ſo hate them that live in it, that they ſtirre up both Magiſtrates and people to hail them out of their high places, where their Steeple and Bells are, to be ſent to priſon, ſtocks, and Bridewel to be whipt, and are mock't, and ſcofft, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ſtoned by thoſe they teach ſo to do: Oh! what a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible thing is here committed in England? the Miniſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo called by men, but not of God, preach for hire, gifts and rewards, and the Rulers and people bear rule by their meanes: Oh woe unto you! what wil your end be, now the Lord God is coming to viſit you for all theſe things!</p>
            <p>The Goſpel that the Miniſters of Chriſt preach, came not to them by man, neither were they taught it of man, but by the revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, and by Chriſt alone without man are they made able Miniſters, not of the Letter, but of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and have power given them from above of the Father to go labour in his vineyard, and to feed the Lambs and ſheep of Chriſt, and to bare their teſtimony of Chriſt the everlaſting Goſpel, whoſe name is the <hi>Word of God,</hi> who is the light of the world, and is the true light that enlightens every one that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth into the word, and that God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all, which is their meſſage, worke, and the gift of God to turn people from darkneſs to the light Chriſt Jeſus, and from the power of Satan unto God, who is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118020:4"/>
            <p>The Miniſters and Teachers of England, ſo called by men, are ſet to School when they are children, to learn to read Engliſh, Latine, Greek and Hebrew, and to conſtrue their Latine, Greek and Hebrew they learn into Engliſh; and when they are by their Schoolmaſter thought fit, then they are ſent to Oxford and Cambridge to learn of men how to preach, and not of Chriſt; and when they have learned of their tutors, how to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact up together out of the ancient Fathers writings which was beyond Sea, and the antient Fathers writings here in <hi>England,</hi> as they call them, the Hiſtories and Scriptures, of all together a form of words in writing which they get over and over, as a Schollar doth his leſſon before he cometh to his maſter to hear if he can ſay it perfectly; ſo likewiſe do they before their tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and others, with their notes writ and laid before them, in their Bibles, and if they can ſay their ſtudied form of prayer, which they have got into their memory, and that which they have compacted together in writing, perfectly in a pulpit, an hour by a glaſs vvithout ſtuttering or ſtammering, and can come downe again out of their Pulpits with their brazen faces un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted, then they are approved of by men to be expert young men, and good Schollars, and will make able Preachers of the Goſpel, as they judge; ſo they receive their degrees of Arts, and are ſet at Liberty from Oxford and Cambridge, to go have a further approving off by men, and of men do receive their commiſſion to Preach, and not of God; ſo that how to preach is taught them by man, and not of God, and what they do Preach they have it not by Revelation from Jeſus Chriſt, but from the Letter, and by works of other mens, their own ſtudy and maginations, which comes out of the bottomleſs Pit, and aſcends up like a ſmoke; take away from them the dead letter and the dead Fathers writings which they have had from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea, and the dead Fathers writings, hiſtories, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords which are in England, vvhich are the inſtruments and means by vvhich they <hi>preach,</hi> and not by <hi>the Spirit,</hi> as their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies full of books will witneſs; and then it will appear in one quarter of a year you ſhall ſcarce have a Sermon preached by any of them that have the weakeſt memories, and very few by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118020:5"/> them that have the ſtrongeſt memories: ſo that it doth plainly appear that they are but Miniſters of the Letter, and not of the Spirit; therefore I deny them all to be any of the Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, and I deny their teachers and approvers, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion-givers, all, from the greateſt to the leaſt, to have any thing to do in this work, for it is the proper work of Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Lord of the Harveſt, and ſaith the Harveſt is great, and the Labourers are few, pray ye therefore, ſaith he, that the Lord of the Harveſt would ſend forth more Labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers into his Vineyard: Therefore ye Commiſſions givers, and Approvers, and ſenders forth of Miniſters, as you call them, who take this work upon your ſelves, ceaſe from your actings herein, and conſider with your ſelves what account you will give unto the Lord of the Harveſt who is coming, and will ſay unto you, who hath required this at your hands that ye have done.</p>
            <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus do declare by the Spirit, that which was from the beginning, which they have heard, and ſeen with their eyes, and looked upon; and their hands have handled of the word of life, and that life which is manifeſted unto them, and live in; whoſe fellowſhip is with the Father and the Son, they declare:</p>
            <p>But thoſe in England, called Miniſters and teachers, having gotten a form of ſome ſound words from the Scriptures, and help of others, they preach by the Letter, and not from the life and power of thoſe that gave the Scriptures forth; ſo that in what they preach they erre, not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God, neither have they heard that which was from the beginning, nor ſeen nor taſted of the word of life, by the Spirit of life, which they preach of, but are as ignorant of the life and power, as they that hear them, whom their words profit not at all, becauſe they come not from the life of them that gave the Scriptures forth, nor ſtand in the counſell of the Lord, therefore they are no Miniſters of Chriſt, but are the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deceivers that are entred into the World, which by their works deny Chriſt come in the fleſh.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118020:5"/>
            <p>The Miniſters and Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt, they are ſent to turn people from darkneſs to the light, Chriſt Jeſus, the ſaviour of their ſouls, the light and life of men, the way to the Father, and the truth, and from the power of Satan unto God, who is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all, and did and do turn ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to righteouſneſs, and for ſo doing are counted deceivers by this Generation, as they have been by former Generations, but are true, and the truth is in them, they being of God, and the whole world lying in wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>Bur the Miniſters, ſo called, in England, which preach in the high places, teach the people lyes, and ſo lead the people into darkneſs from the light; and now I appeal to that of God in all your conſciences, both Miniſters, ſo called, and people, for who hath taught the people to call the high places, with the ſteeples and bells in them the Church? have not you their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters? and is this any other than a lye, for the Church is in God, the father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the body of Chriſt is the church, which is the ground and pillar of truth, made up of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſtones, Chriſt Jeſus being the chief corner-ſtone, which you builders, called Miniſters, refuſe, and is become a ſtone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and a Rock of offence to you, but you that ſtumble thereat, great ſhal be your fall. And who hath taught the people that God dwells in thoſe places, called the church, in a more ſpecial manner than in any other place, but you their teachers? and is not that another lye? for God dwells not in temples made with hands: and who teaches the people to ſay God is worſhipped in thoſe places, but you their Miniſters, ſo called? and is not that a lye? for God is a ſpirit, and is worſhipped in ſpirit and in truth, and not in thoſe high places. And when a company of proud high minded people, ſcoffers, ſcorners, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, earthly minded, lovers of Money, the Root of all evill, Whores, and Whore-mongers, Adulterers, Fornicators, Thieves, Curſers, ſwearers, Lyars, Drunkards, Fighters Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellers Reprobates which know not that Chriſt is in them, are all gathered together at your call and invitation, to come cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily to that which you call a <hi>SACRAMENT,</hi> and ſet together to eat the <hi>Bread</hi> that you break, and when you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118020:6"/> give it to them, that they muſt take and eat this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that Chriſt dyed for them, and be thankfull; and when you pour out the wine, do not you tell them that the blood of Jeſus Chriſt was ſhed for them, and for the Remiſſion of their Sins? Do not you herein tell them lyes? Are not the wicked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for the day of judgement? And the wicked, and all they that forget God, ſhall be turned into hell, their condemnation is ordained of old, being none of the ſeed that the promiſe is to, nor the Sheep that the good Shepheard laid down his life for.</p>
            <p>And who hath taught the people to call that which you call a Sacrament of the body and blood of Chriſt, the Supper of the Lord, and the Table of the Lord? have not you their Miniſters (ſo called) taught them, both by preaching and writing, which are lyes? for I tel both you, and all ſuch perſons afore named, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt neither Sups with you, nor you with him, for there is no fellowſhip betwixt Chriſt and <hi>Beliall,</hi> nor no communication betwixt Light and Darkneſs: and that which you call the table of the Lord, you make it a table of devills, for it is no other, for he that committeth ſin is of the devill: and are not ye, and all ſuch aforementioned, committers of ſin? and ſo of the Devill your Father, whoſe works you all do, and ye cannot partake of the table of the Lord, and the table of devils.</p>
            <p>And who hath taught the people and made them believe that when their children are ſprinckled with a little water on their faces, which you call baptiſm, that then they become mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the church, and chriſtians; do not you their teachers teach them ſo, that they become members of Harlots, and Members of the Synagogue of Satan, ſetting together in the Idolls-tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, being led captive by you, ever learning, but never able to come to the knowledg of the truth by your preaching, ſo that ye are none of the Miniſters of Chriſt, but are the evill men and ſeducers, that wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived; Ah! wo unto you ye blind guides, called Miniſters of England) which lead the blind out of their way, ye are all under the Curſe of God, for curſed is he that leadeth the blind out of his way, and the wrath of God is to be revealed againſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118020:6"/> you all, who hold the truth in unrighteouſneſs, tribulation and anguiſh be upon every ſoul that doth evil, ye workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
            <p>And again who teacheth the people to make ſongs of the Saints conditions, and to turn the Scriptures, which is a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the things, which are moſt certainly known and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved amongſt us, into lyes and blaſphemies? do not you the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of this Nation, ſo called, teach them who are proud hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, high minded people, drunkards, ſwearers, lyars, whores, and whore-mongers, covetous, envious, malicious, ſcorners, ſcoffers, thieves and murderers, when they are met together in the high places of the Nations; Come (ſay they) let us ſing to the Praiſe and Glory of God, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 116.1, 2: I love the Lord, becauſe my voice and prayer heard hath he, whenas they that walk in Darkneſs hate the Light, for God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all; and the wicked through the pride of his heart, wil not ſeek after God, for God is not in all his thoughts: The wicked ſay unto God, depart from us, we deſire not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of thy wayes, and what is the Almighty that we ſhould ſerve him? And what profit ſhould we have if we pray unto him? ſay the wicked that are friends of the world and enemies to God; yet their teachers wil teach them to lye, and ſay, I love the Lord, becauſe he hath heard my prayers, when the prayers of the wicked is abominable to the Lord.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. ver. 97: where they are taught to ſing, <hi>What great deſire and fervent love do I bear to thy Law?</hi> whenas the wicked turn away their ears from hearing the law of God, caſt it behind their backs, and will have none of his counſel, but deſpiſe reproof, crying, <hi>it is a hard ſaying, who can bear it?</hi> they wil have none of his wayes, becauſe they hate knowledg, and choſe not the fear of the Lord, and yet ſay in their ſongs, <hi>they delight in his Law,</hi> of which they are not aſhamed.</p>
            <p>And again, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139: ver. 21, 22. ſay they, let us ſing to the praiſe and glory of God, <hi>Hate J not them that hate the Lord?</hi> I <hi>hate them with unfeigned hate:</hi> but the world love their own, and hate thoſe that are not of the world, the wicked plotteth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118020:7"/> againſt the juſt, and gnaſheth upon him with his teeth, and bleſſeth the covetous whom the Lord abhorreth, his mouth is full of curſing, deceit and fraud, under his tongue is miſchief and vanity, he ſetteth in lurking places; in ſecret places doth he mu der the innocent, and in his pride doth perſecute the upright in heart.</p>
            <p>And yet they will ſing <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16. ver. 2, 3. That they give their Goods to the Saints, the Faithfull Flock that in vertue excell: But ſaith Chriſt, when ſaw ye me an hungry, and gave me meat; thirſty, and gave me drink; naked, and cloathed me, or the leaſt of theſe my little ones? Did not the wicked give the juſt and pure in heart, Gall for his meat, and in his thirſt, Vinegar to drink? Do they not cauſe the naked to lodge without cloathing, ſo that they have no covering in the cold? and here the mercies of the wicked are cruelty, and yet their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; ſo called, teaches and leads the wicked to ſing that they give their goods to the Saints on earth.</p>
            <p>And in the 119. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. they ſing; With zeal and wrath I am conſumed, and even pined away; when at the very ſame time the eyes of ſome ſtick out with fatneſs, and in their own fat they are encloaſed, and have more than heart can wiſh, his breaſts are full of Milk, and his bones are full of Marrow, and he encreaſes in riches, and is not in ſorrow like other men:</p>
            <p>Again they ſay, let us ſing to the praiſe and glory of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96: verſe 12. If I for griefe and paine of heart, in Sackcloath uſe to walk; and at the very ſame time their filthy Fleſh is adorned with Silk, and Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Lace, Rings, and Rich Attire, coſtly Arraiment, and not with modeſt Apparell, but are haughty, and walk with ſtretched out Necks, with wanton Eyes, and tinckling with their Feet as they go along, ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their dayes in Pleaſures and Vanity, upon the VIALL TIMBRELL and HARP, and rejoyce at the ſound of the ORGAN, living in Chambring and Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs, Rioteouſneſs, Gluttony, and Drunkenneſs, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118020:7"/> never weare Sackcloath in all their lives, nor you their tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers neither:</p>
            <p>Now all you that are called Miniſters, do but ſee and behold what you do, do you not teach the people to Sing and ſay that which they do not, nor your ſelves neither, ſo that you teach the people to Lye, and Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme, which is the work of the Devill, your Father, who was a Lyar from the beginning, whoſe Children ye are, and for him are compaſſing Sea and Land to make one profit, and when he is made, you make him two fold more the Childe of Hell then he was before, by leading them from Light into Darkneſs, and from the TRUTH into LYES, as is here made manifeſt; Depart ye Workers of Iniquity into utter Darkneſs, and receive your Portion among the Hypocrites, and all the Damned in Hell, for I deny you all to be any Miniſters of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The MINISTERS of CHRIST are all of one heart, and one minde, and agree together in the Unity of the SPIRIT and live in the Bond of Love and Peace, being guided, by the ſpirit of GOD, which is one, and leads up to one God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Cnriſt, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one Truth, and Saviour of their ſouls, Chriſt Jeſus the Light, one in all, the Light of the World, that enlightens every one that comes into the World, and is the Condemnation of all the World that walk in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Hate the Light, God is Light, and in him is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at all, and this is their meſſage which they declare, in which they all agree:</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118020:8"/>
            <p>Thoſe in England, called Miniſters, they agree not in one, for they cry, lo here ſaith one, lo here ſaith another, and ſaith the <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> Government is the true way to worſhip God in: Another he ſaith the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Government is the true way, and in it is God worſhipped in ſpirit and in truth: Others are for the <hi>Independant</hi> Government, and they ſeparate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a little from the other too, and ſay that is the way to worſhip God, and this, ſay they, is the true way. But being all in the many forms of bodyly exerciſe, which profiteth little, and out of the true worſhiping of God in ſpirit and truth, which is profitable unto all things.</p>
            <p>One ſaith that ſprinckling of Infants, with the words ſpoken by him, is Baptiſm, and an Ordinance of God, and ſo he is for having all men and womens children baptized, as he calls it: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother he ſaith that none ought to be baptized but the children of believing parents, and will baptize no other, as he calls them: Another ſaith that believers that can give a good account of their faith, are to be baptized by dipping, or plunging all the body in water, and no other: and ſo here they are all in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny baptiſms, not baptizing, nor being baptized with that one Baptiſm of Chriſt, which is by Fire and the Spirit into his death, by one Spirit, into the one Body, wherein there is Unity, which they are all out of.</p>
            <p>Neither do they agree in the one Faith, for they tell people of miraculous Faith, and of Hiſtoricall Faith, and of a dead Faith, and a juſtifying Faith, which they know not, nor are in, but are in the many Faiths, and out of that one Faith the juſt lives by, that purifies their hearts, and is their Victory by which they overcome the world:</p>
            <p>Some of them will receive all that come to their Sacrament, as they call it; others wil receive none to partake with them of their Sacrament, but thoſe who are of their own judgment and practiſe in worſhip with them; but at their Sacrament none of them ſit at the Lords Table, nor diſcern the Lords Body, nor eat nor drink of the bread and water of life, but feed upon that which is carnall and not ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>Again, one preaches one Doctrine, another he preaches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118020:8"/> to it, and one ſaith this is the meaning of this Scripture, and another ſaith it muſt be taken in another ſenſe; another ſaith that the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> or the <hi>Greek</hi> Tranſlation (which they call the Originall, but is the confounded languages) renders it thus; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother he comes and ſaith, this is the true meaning, and he brings his Author for it, an old Fathers writing that is dead long ago; but none of them have the ſenſe and true meaning of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from the life, which the ſpirit of God that gave the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures forth, which is the Key of <hi>David,</hi> that opens and no man ſhuts, and ſhuts and no man opens, but the ſenſe and meaning is by them in their many meanings given out contrary, which is from their own imaginations, the bottomleſs pit, and being written, or preached by them, is the ſmoak that aſcends there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and thus they twiſt and twine here and there, beguiling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſouls, and by good words and faire ſpeeches, deceive the ſimple hearted, which are ever learning of them, but never able to come to the knowledg of the truth, becauſe they are led by thoſe blind guides, which know not the way to the father of life, nor to Chriſt Jeſus the ſaviour of their ſouls; ſo the blind leading the blind, fall both into the ditch, becauſe they ſee not the way they go in, and yet theſe leaders are called Miniſters and Paſtors, but are not, but are blaſphemers and lyars, turning here and turning there, ſaying this is the way, and that is the way; O ye ſerpents, ye generation of vipers! how can ye eſcape the damnation of hell? as were your Fathers ſo are ye; fill you up therefore the meaſure of their iniquities, that all the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgments of God may be poured out upon you all, who hold the truth of God in unrighteouſneſs? for now is the Lord God gathering his army together, and coming to Battle, their weapons are not carnal but ſpirituall, and mighty to the throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down of ſtrong holds, and the Beaſt, and the Whore, and the falſe Prophet which deceive them that received the mark of the Beaſt, and worſhip his Image, ſhall be taken, and together caſt into the lake that burns with fire and brimſtone, your juſt reward, ye ſerpents.</p>
            <p>To the Miniſters and Apoſtles of Chriſt, is given the gift of the ſpirit, to profit withall in the work of the Miniſtry, for the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118020:9"/> perfecting of the Saints, and for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till they all come into the unity of the faith and the knowledg of the ſon of God, unto a perfect man, unto the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt their Maſter, and for their ſo doing their praiſe is not of man, but of God the father of Light, with whom their reward is, and from whence every good and perfect gift cometh that they have received, and the wiſdom they have received is from above, and is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle and eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality, and without hypocriſie.</p>
            <p>But the wiſdom that the Miniſters (ſo called in England by men) have, is not from above, becauſe it is earthly, and ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and devilliſh, by which wiſdom neither they, nor the reſt of the world, know God, neither can they know him that hath not the ſon, for God hath no union with them, neither doth he make himſelf manifeſt unto them who live in ſtrife, and bitter envying and confuſion, and every evill work as they do, by ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the Magiſtrates and people to take counſell together againſt the Lord, and againſt his anointed, &amp; if the Magiſtrates will not do as they would have them, they will rail againſt them openly in their Pulpits, and wreſt the Scriptures to their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and their own deſtruction; and thoſe Magiſtrates that will cauſe the people to hale the Servants of the Lord out of their Synagogues to the Stocks, and Priſons, and Bride-wells, to be whipt and beat, and put into Dungeons (as the Rulers, Elders, Scribes, and high Prieſts did in the dayes of the Apoſtles) ſuch Magiſtrates and Rulers ſhall have their praiſe; but ſaith Chriſt, what ye do to the leaſt of theſe my little ones, I take as done unto my ſelf, and it were better for you that a Milſtone were hanged about your necks, and ye caſt into the Sea, then that you ſhould offend the leaſt of theſe little ones, for you that touch them touch the Apple of his eye: and plainly I tel you all that are of men called Miniſters, that all the ſtuff you labour for, and by your works have got together (it being not the gift of God) doth not perfect the Saints, nor edifie the body of Chriſt, for you your ſelves being dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by your dead Letter, dead Works of Doctrines, Reaſons,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:118020:9"/> and uſes raiſe the dead; for it is the living that raiſes the dead to praiſe the Lord in the Land of the living, as in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures you may read, that it was Chriſt that raiſed up <hi>Lazarus</hi> out of the grave, where he lay dead, which is to you a myſtery: Wo unto you hypocrites, that do all to be heard and ſeen of men: And wo unto you that all men ſpeak well of, whoſe praiſe is of the men of the world, and not of God, that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected of men, and do reſpect the mens perſons of the world, and have the great mens perſons of the world in admiration for advantage ſake, and love ſalutations by the way, and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the Market places, and to be called of men Maſters; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ye thus to be out of the Doctrine of Chriſt, and in the practiſe of the Heathen, Scribes, Phariſees, and Hypocrites, therefore I deny you all to be any of the Miniſters of Chriſt Jeſus, and your voice I diſown, it being the voice of a ſtranger which I am fled from. And now all you that are by men cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Miniſters of England, you are weighed in the ballance, and found too light; your Kingdome is divided and ſhall be taken from you, for it is given to another, even to him to whom all the ends of the Earth are given for his poſſeſſion, who will break you with a Rod of Iron, and daſh you in pieces like a Potters Veſſell, for the blood-thirſtie and deceitfull men ſhall not live out half their dayes. Weep and howle, weep and howl, all ye who are called of men Miniſters of England, who have ſate at eaſe, deckt like a Queen, and faired deliciouſly, and have felt no ſorrow like other men, for now is your miſery coming upon you like an armed man, prepare your ſelves, put on your ſtrength, make ready your weopens, and come and ſee if you can withſtand the Lord in his fury, or overcome him by all your ſtrength. God gave the Woman <hi>Iezebell,</hi> that calls her ſelf a Prophetteſs, and takes upon her to teach and ſeduce my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to commit fornication with her, ſpace to repent of her fornication, and ſhe has not repented; therefore behold, ſaith the Lord, I wil caſt her upon a bed of torments, and them that have committed adultery with her, and great ſhall be their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, except they repent, therefore while you have a little time prize it, and break of your ſins by repentance, ceaſe from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118020:10"/> the evill of your doings, and learn of God to do wel, and if you will return, return to the Lord God, who is gracious and mercifull, and in patience hath born long with ye all the time that ye were learning to preach, who then ſaw what you were going about to do, and all your actings in that time, and all the time you have been preaching, which hath brought forth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but vanity and lyes, for all the profeſſion of Religion that you have taught the people all this while ſtands in a lye, and their fear of the Lord is taught them by your precepts, who are men; for what do you, or they all poſſeſs of what you profeſs? nothing at all, therefore it is lightneſs, and vanity, and is unto the Lord as loath ſome, as if you cut off a Dogs head, or offered to him Swines Fleſh in abominable broath; nay he will not accept of the hire of a whore that you bring before him, it all ſtincks in his Noſtrills, and is caſt out from before him, as a filthy Dung-hill. Your ſacrifice is abomination, and all your works are as filthy Rags; and as the cloath of a monſtrious woman, ye are defiled, and with your defilements you defile. Oh ſtop your mouthes and be ſilent, ye men who are called. Miniſters of the Goſpell, but are not the Miniſters of Chriſt! and let ſhame cover your faces in the preſence of the Lord God of life and power, who is of purer eyes than to behold ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</p>
            <p>Therefore all people, High and Low, Rich and Poor, Bond and Free, who have been hearing and learning for many years together of thoſe you call Miniſters, and are not the Miniſters of Chriſt, by whoſe Miniſtry ye are not yet come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the truth by their long preaching: Ceaſe from man, whoſe breath is in his Noſtrills, and ſpend not your money for that which is not bread, nor your labour for that which ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies not, but return to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the Light, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and Biſhop of your ſouls, who ſaith, come learn of me, hearken diligently, hear and your ſouls ſhal live, who filleth the hungry with good things, and the rich he ſends empty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: A Prophet hath the Lord God raiſed up amongſt you, hear ye him, ſaith the Lord, in all things, who teaches the way of truth and holyneſs, without which no man ſhal ſee the Lord,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118020:10"/> and this is my beloved Son, ſaith God, he that refuſeth to hear him ſhal be cut off from the land of the living, for God ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the world, that he ſent his only begotten Son into the world, and this is the condemnation, the light which is into the world come, Chriſt Jeſus the Son of God the light of the world that makes manifeſt in you ſin and evill deeds, and ſhews you all things that ever you have done in your life time; and this is Chriſt the Prophet, that meets with you whitherſoever you go, and ſhews you that ſin which you have committed in ſecret, which none can reprove you for but he that ſeeth in ſecret and in the dark places; and this is Chriſt the light of the world, that enlightneth every one that comes into the world, and is made manifeſt in the conſcience, and to as many as receive him, and believe on his name, he gives them power to become the Sons of God; whom he teacheth in his wayes, ſo that they need not another to teach them, being the children of the Lord, are taught of the Lord, and Sons of God are led by the Spirit of God into all truth, and can read the Law writ in their hearts. Now people every one of you, mind that which makes manifeſt your ſin unto you, and checks you for the ſin you commit, by bringing upon you tribulation, and anguiſh upon every one that doth evill. Thoſe that walk in darkneſs hate Chriſt Ieſus, the light that is come into the world, and is the condemnation of thoſe that love darkneſs and not the light becauſe their deeds be evil, and the light reproves them becauſe their works are of the Devil; but he that doeth truth cometh to the light, that his deeds may be tryed whether they be of God, who is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all: Now people ye have a Light in your conſciences, which makes manifeſt your ſin unto you, unto which ye do wel if ye take heed, as unto a Light that ſhineth in a dark place, until the day dawn, and the Day-ſtar ariſe in your hearts, which is the ſure word of propheſie; and the Son of righteouſneſs that riſes with healing in his wings, therefore come to him that ye may have life, wait upon him who is worthy of waiting on, who wil anoint you with an unc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which you ſhal know al things, ſo that you need not to be taught of man, and gives to every one freely, without
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118020:11"/> money, and without price, bread to the hungrie, water to the thirſty ſoul, clothing to the naked, eye-ſalve to the blinde; the poor he fils with good things, and thoſe that fear him ſhall not want; but the whole need no Phyſician, and the rich he ſends empty away: Therefore while you have time, people prize it, draw nigh unto God, and he will draw nigh unto you; clenſe your hands you ſinners, and purifie your hearts, ye double-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ceaſe from evil, and put not from you the evil day afarr off, but put away from you the evil of your doings, and learne the fear of the Lord, which is to depart from ſinne, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of pure wiſdome, which teaches how to do righteouſlie, juſtlie, and to walk humblie with the Lord, and this is the grace of God that appears to all men, that brings ſalvation, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches men to denie all ungodlineſs, and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberlie, righteouſlie, and godlike, holie as he is holie, in this preſent world, in all manner of converſation; here is life and death ſet before you, people, chooſe which you will; for if you neglect ſo great ſalvation, how do you think to eſcape the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of hel? Therefore people in the fear of the Lord, ſearch and try all things, forſake the evil and hold faſt that which is good of God, who is faithful and deceives none, for the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven is within you, and the many deceivers are in the world, look not out at them, neither go after them, but keep your heart with all diligence, for out of them are the iſſues of life, for in Iſrael abides in his tents, and do not ſay but in your life-time you have been warned of the manie decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, by him who is a lover of your ſouls; who is knowne by the name of</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Clark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth a fountain ſend forth at the ſame place ſweet water and bitter? Can the Fig-tree, my brethren, bare olive-berries, either a Vine Figs? ſo can no Fountain both yeeld ſalt water and freſh, <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118020:11"/>
            <p> Here followeth a Declaration of ſome Lawes made by the pope, and the popiſh Saxon Kings, who governed <hi>England,</hi> and were the firſt erecters of all the Abbies, Monaſteries, Fryer-houſes, Chantry-houſes, Cathedrals, &amp;c. as J have them out of the firſt and ſecond volums of the <hi>Books of Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEnedict, an Abbot of the Monaſtery of Peter and Paul at Wirr, brought with him from Rome one John, the Arch-chantler, who firſt taugt in England how to ſing in the Quire after the manner of Rome.</p>
            <p>In the yeer 747. at the beginning of King Edgberts reign, the Synod of Biſhops diſputed the profit of ſinging of the Pſalms in the Church as they called it, and made a decree that with a modeſt voice they ſhould ſing in the Church, ſo by them called.</p>
            <p>In the Yeer 747. at the beginning of King Edgberts Reign, the Sinod of Biſhops diſputed the profit of ſinging the Pſalms in the Church, as they called it, and made a decree that with a modeſt voice they ſhould ſing in the Church, ſo by them cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            <p>In the Yeer 924. King Ethelſtone, <hi>alias</hi> Atelſtone, made a Law that fifty Pſalms ſhould be daily ſung in the Church, as he called it, for the King.</p>
            <p>In the Yeer DCCXII. King Inas <hi>alias</hi> Ina, or Iue, made a Law, that Infants ſhould be baptized within thirtie daies: This King Ina or Iue, gave up the Government of the Kingdome of England unto Ethelardus his Nephew, and he himſelf took up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the habit of a poor man, and with great devotion tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled to Rome, and was there made a Monk, and the ſaid King Ina made a Law, that the firſt fruits of all that was ſowne, to be paid at the day of St Martine, as he called it, and about 720 he cauſed thorowout his Dominions, that everie houſe that had a chimney ſhould pay a pennie to the Pope in the name of Saint Peter: this King was the firſt that brought up Peter-pence in England.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:118020:12"/>
            <p>In the Year 933. King <hi>Atelſtone</hi> made a Law, that Tythes ſhould be paid of all the proper Goods, as well of living Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle as of Corn, and firſt fruits of the Ground.</p>
            <p>In the Year 940. King <hi>Edmond</hi> made a Law, that Tythes, with the firſt Fruits of every mans crap, ſhould be duly paid.</p>
            <p>In the Year 959. King <hi>Edgar</hi> ordained and decreed, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Liberties and Freedomes of the Church, as they called it, that Tythes, and firſt fruits of Corn, and <hi>Peter</hi>-Pence, be all paid.</p>
            <p>Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the third (with all his Rabble of Monks and Fryers) was the firſt that brought in private Tythes, to be paid at Eaſter, about the time of King <hi>Johns</hi> raign in England.</p>
            <p>Now people here you may in part ſee who were the authors of Tythes to be paid out of the fruits of your labour. So here follows what the Church was the tythes were paid to, and in particular, what the tythes were that was paid and received.</p>
            <p>THeir Church was a company of ſtrange Puiſſant, counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, holy, idle Vagabonds, and ravening wolves, ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led (by one <hi>Simond Fiſh</hi>) which were Abbuts, Priors, Deacons, Arch-Deacons, Suffragans, Prieſts, Monks, Canons, Fryers, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners, and Sumners, theſe had the goodlieſt Lordſhips, Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, Lands, and Territories in the Land in their poſſeſſion, and in particular, the tythes they had was the tenth part of all the Corn, Medow, Paſture, Graſs, Wood, Coults, Calves, Lambs, Pigs, Geeſe, and Chickens, and the tenth part of every ſervants wages, the tenth part of Wool, Milk, Honey, Wax, Cheeſe and Butter; and they looked ſo narrowly to their profits, that if they had not every tenth Egg, the women could not have their due at Eaſter, but were counted <hi>Hereticks.</hi> Again they had four offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring-dayes, privy-tythes, offerings to their <hi>Pilgrimages,</hi> money for <hi>Diriges</hi> to be ſung at the Buriall of every man and child, or elſe they would accuſe their friends of Hereſie: And beſides this they had money for probates of <hi>Teſtaments Mortuaries,</hi> and <hi>Confesſions</hi> hallowing of Churches, Alters, ſuper Alters, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells, and Bells, by curſing of men, and abſolving them again:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118020:12"/> Finally, the infinite number of the five Orders of Fryars, who had of every houſe a penny a year; the five Orders of Fryars had five pence a year of every houſe; and in King <hi>Henry</hi> the eights dayes, the ſum being caſt up to him, what came in yearly to theſe five Orders of Fryers, it did amount to 430333. 6. s. 8. d. a year, as is ſet down in the Book of Martyrs (by one <hi>Simond Fiſh</hi>) and not above four hundred years before that time, they had not one penny, for the ancient <hi>Britains</hi> ever ſtood free from ſuch burthens, till that time that the pope and the Saxon Kings laid them on us, who now bear the ſame in part, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after is made appear.</p>
            <p>And now you ſhal ſee if thoſe now in England, called Miniſters, do not tread in the ſame ſteps, and how far they come ſhort of their forefathers: Firſt, it is undenyable that they baptize Infants within thirty daies, according to the law of the Monkiſh King, <hi>Ina,</hi> and not according to any law of God (that they have to ſprinckle little children on the face with water, &amp; call it baptiſm) but by the popes, and their own imaginations, conſequences, and conceivings of the Scriptures:</p>
            <p>And according to the Biſhops decree, and the Kings law, they ſing, and teach to be ſung in the high places where the Steeples and Bels are, the Pſalms and Saints conditions, that they two Poets, <hi>Sternhold</hi> and <hi>Hopkins,</hi> with others, have turned into Meeter, by their fallen wiſdome, and not by the ſpirit of God; but they wil ſay they have a rule in the Scripture to ſing Pſalms by, <hi>Is any merry? let him ſing Pſalms:</hi> but what have drunkards ſwearers, proud and covetous perſons to do to make ſongs of the Saints conditions, that was never none of their own? or to take the name of God in their mouthes, ſeeing they hate to be reformed; therefore ye ſingers, ſtop your mouthes, and be ſilent before the Lord God of heaven and earth, for it were better for you to be in the houſe of mourning, than in the high places of mirth, for the day of the Lord is coming, wherein your ſongs ſhall be turned into howling, and your joie into bitter lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</p>
            <p>And as concerning Tithes, do not the Miniſters of England, ſo called, take tithes of the people, even the tenth part of their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118020:13"/> Corn, and Hey; Wool, Lambs, Pigs, Geeſe, Eggs; and have they not tithes of Coults, Calves, and dead ſheep-skins, and of Bees, from whence the honey and wax comes, and tithe apples, pears, hemp and flax, and in ſome places of this land tithe milk, and at Eaſter ſome part of the ſervants wages, and Eaſter Recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; they have two pence of the husband, and two pence for the wife, and two pence for the chimney, and herein they out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrip the pope, for he had but a penny a chimney, and they have got beyond the five Orders of Fryers, for they had but five pence a year of a houſe, and they have ſix pence a year, beſides the two pence for a ſon, and two pence for a daughter, and two pence for a prentice, if a man have them, and they come to their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: And have they not money for buriall of the dead, and as it was the Monks office to mourn, ſo will they put on a black mourning ſuit of the parties gift that is dead, and imitate the Monk in his diſſembling-mourning, heathen-like, who made cuttings in their fleſh, and bauldneſs between their eyes for the dead, which the children of Iſrael were not to do, becauſe God had choſen them to be a holy and peculiar people to himſelf.</p>
            <p>And again, if the people did not pay the Abbuts, Priors, Prieſts, &amp;c. their tithes and money, they accuſed them for hereticks, and ſo for hereſie they proceeded againſt them; and you may ſee in the Book of Martyrs what became of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, they were tyed to a ſtake, and fire and faggots put to them and burnt by that bloody generation of men.</p>
            <p>And do not theſe in England, called Miniſters? if men who own Chriſt, and for conſcience ſake cannot pay them tithes, they will ſue them at Law, and proceed to make diſtreſs upon their goods for trebble damages, or get an Order from a Court to ſend their bodies to priſon, there to lye at great charges to the undoing of them and their families; and the ſame ſpirit that c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rcies them on to do this, wil carry them on to do more if they had but a Popiſh King, and a law, and popiſh Magiſtrates that would put it in execution, And again, have they not the beſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and faireſt houſes, that are in moſt Countrey Villages in England, yea and in ſome Towns to: and now people you may ſee how far your Preachers, called Miniſters, go in the ſteps of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118020:13"/> their forefathers, as their forefathers were ſo are they; but they wil ſay they denie the pope, and the Biſhops, and their orders: I anſwer, I know they do in words, but in their works they own them; ſo in their words they profeſs Chriſt, but in their works they denie him, for they that pay tithes, and they that receive tithes, both by their works deny Chriſt come in the fleſh, for Chriſt is the end of the Law, for righteouſneſs to every one that believeth; the prieſthood, and the Levites tithes, and firſt fruit-offerings and ſacrifices, ordained by the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Alter and Tabernacle, and the Temple, were all but figures and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of good things to come; now Chriſt Jeſus, the ſum and ſubſtance of all theſe, being come, the prieſthood is changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, who is made after the power of an endleſs life; there is of neceſſitie made a change of the law alſo, by which law they had a command to take tithes of the people; but Chriſt being come, put down the <hi>priests</hi> and the <hi>Levites,</hi> that were maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the firſt fruits and tithes, and he himſelf being in their place, he did not take tithes, for he had no ſtore-houſe to put them in; for ſaith he, the Foxes have holes, and the Birds of the aire have neſts, but the Son of Man hath no where to lay his head, ye may read in the Scriptures; and ſo he had no certain dwelling place on the earth; for he was ſometimes on the ſea-ſide, ſometimes upon the ſea, and in the WILDERNESSE and in deſert places, ſometimes at Jeruſalem, and went round about the villages teaching, and upon the mountains, and went into the land of Genazereth, into the villages, cities, and countries to Tyre and Sidon, and from thence to the ſea of Gallilee, through the midſt of the coaſts of Decapolis, he being come to do the will of his father; he had no long time to ſtay in a place to take tithes, neither did he give any command to his Apoſtles and Diſciples to receive any tithes, for he commanded them to go into all Nations, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. and he ſent them by two and two, <hi>Mark</hi> 6. ver. 7: and he ſent them to preach the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, and to heal the ſick, and they departed and went through the towns, preaching the Goſpel, and healing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, <hi>Luke.</hi> 9. ver. 2.6. and ſaith Chriſt to them, freely have ye received, freely give, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. ver: 8. and into whatſoever ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ye enter into, and they receive you, eat ſuch things as are ſet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118020:14"/> before you: and into whatſoever Houſe ye enter, firſt ſay, peace be to this houſe, and if the Son of peace be there, your peace ſhall reſt upon it, and in the ſame Houſe abide til ye depart, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking ſuch things as they give, for the labourer is worthy of his Hire, <hi>Luke</hi> 10: ver. 7, 8. <hi>Mark.</hi> 6. ver. 10, ſo that their meat and their drink that was ſet before them by theſe that received them, was their wages, and not tithes. Here it plainly appears that thoſe that owned Chriſt and received his Apoſtles, they paid no tithes, neither did the Apoſtles receive any tithes, nor Chriſt neither,</p>
            <p>To whom were tithes paid? and who were they that paid tithes? thoſe that did not own Chriſt Jeſus, but denyed him to be the Son of God, ſaying, is not this the carpenter, the Son of <hi>Mary,</hi> the brothers of Iames and Ioſeph, &amp;c. but the chiefe prieſts, ſcribes, and phariſees, rulers and elders, theſe received not Chriſt, not owned him to be the Son of God, theſe paid tithes of mint and comin, annis, rue, and all manner of herbs, and crucified the Lord of glory; ſo that it is plainly ſeen, that thoſe that pleaded for tithes, and paid and received tithes after Chriſt came, were thoſe that denied Chriſt come in the fleſh, both by their words and works; and as it was then, ſo it is now, for thoſe now in theſe dayes, that profeſs Chriſt in word to be the Son of God, and pay tithes, and receive tithes, as the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Miniſters of England, ſo called, do by their works de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him: and thoſe that deny him to be Prieſt and Prophet, deny him to be King and Law-giver; as the Pope, and popiſh Kings and Prieſts, who (contrary to his Law, <hi>Swear not at all</hi>) in their own wills made ſeverall forms of oathes and laws to compell people to ſwear by, one form of an Oath to ſwear by to the Pope, another form of Oath, called the Oath of Supremiſie; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother form of an Oath, called the Oath of Allegience; another form of Oath, called the Oath of Abjuration, one form of an Oath for Judges and other Magiſtrates and Officers to ſwear by, and ſo likewiſe for witneſſes, and all were to ſwear upon the four Evangeliſts, or their hand upon the Bible, or elſe they muſt hold their hands up and ſwear, all which way of ſwearing is contrary to the Law which is holy, juſt, and good, which is
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118020:14"/> given out by the pure Law-giver, Chriſt Jeſus, Emanuel, God with us, who ſaith ſwear not at all, neither by Heaven, for it is Gods throne, nor by the earth, for it is his foot-ſtool, nor by Ieruſalem, for it is the City of the living God; nor by thy head, for thou canſt not make one haire white nor black; he that ſweareth by the Altar, ſweareth by all things thereon, and he that ſweareth by the Temple, ſweareth hy him that dwelleth therein; and he that ſweareth by Heaven, ſweareth by the throne of God, and by him that ſitteth thereon: and he that ſweareth by the Bible, ſweareth not only by it, but ſweareth at once by all things therein declared of; and he that holdeth up his hand, and ſweareth by it, ſweareth by him that made it; and he that ſweareth committeth ſin, and is a Tranſgreſſor of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Law of God, and he that committeth ſin is of the Devill. And now thou Pope that was the inventer of the forms of Oathes, and ye Popiſh Kings and Rulers, which make Laws to compell men to ſwear, and you who are called Miniſters, who teach people, and ſay that they might ſwear when they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led before Magiſtrates: Oh ye enemies of God! by whom do your children caſt out devills? Doth not he that committeth ſin by ſwearing, puniſh, or cauſe to be puniſhed, him that tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth your Law, or elſe without an oath, he that is a tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor is not puniſhed? Do not you herein go about to caſt out de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills by the power of Belzebub? Or do you think ever to clenſe the Land of evil doers by ſwearing? I tel you nay, the Land is not clenſed of evill doers, becauſe juſtice is not ſpeedily execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, therefore the hearts of the ſons of men are ſet on to do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; and where are the hands of wicked men more ſtrengthned, and evill doers more encouraged to do evil, than by lying ſo long together in Goals? Let the tranſgreſſors be ſpeedily brought to juſtice, &amp; the innocent quit, leaſt he be defiled by him that is guilty: So long as the murderer lives after the murder is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the land lies polluted in blood. Let the thiefe that is taken ſtealing reſtore fourfold, &amp; if he have not wherewith to reſtore, let him be ſold for his theft, that he ſteal no more, but labour with his hands the thing that is good, &amp; in the ſweat of his brows to eat his own bread. A word is enough to the wiſe, but a fool wil not hear, nor learn wiſdom.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:118020:15"/>
            <p>The Miniſters of Chriſt Ieſus taught the people, ſaying, above all things, my brethren, ſwear not at all, neither by heaven, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by earth, neither by any other oath, leaſt ye fal into condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but let your yea be yea, and your nay nay, for ſaith Chriſt, whatſoever is more than theſe cometh of evill, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. Swear not at all: But you will ſay, this of Chriſt is meant by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary ſwearing, but whoever thou art, by thy earthly carnal wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom knoweſt not what Chriſt means, it being hid from thy eyes. And the natural man perceives not the things of God, neither can he do, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned: And againe, Is there not in this Land ſwearing before Magiſtrates every day in one place or other, City or Town, before one Magiſtrate or other, or elſe the Goals would not be fill'd ſo full as they bee, and ſo manie bound over to appear at Aſſizes and Seſſions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other convictions for ſwearing, and drunkenneſs, and yet there is never the leſs; and I am ſure it is common enough, ſwearing at Terms, Sizes, Quarter-Seſſions, Court-Leets, and other Courts; and would you have it commonner then every day? Oh pitiful! the Land mourns, becauſe of Oaths, and you who are called Miniſters, ſtop your mouths for ſhame, and preach no more contrary to Chriſts command, whoſe Law which is pure, ye make of none effect, by upholding mens tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: And now all ye who are ſwearing by any oath what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, be ye warned, for the day of the Lord God is coming, wherein ye ſhal give an account for every idle word, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very oath you ſwear, and for all things done in the body what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, the flying Role is gone forth, and the curſe is entring into the houſe of the thief, and into the houſe of the ſwearer, and the Lord God wil be a ſwift witneſs againſt him that ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and againſt him that ſweareth falſly.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay an Oath bindes men to ſpeake the truth; therefore it is neceſſary that witneſſes ſhould ſwear, that they may ſpeak truth.</p>
            <p>Anſwer, It is in a mans minde before he come to a court or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, what he knows of the thing he is to ſpeak of, and ſo likewiſe there is a reſolution in the party what hee will ſpeak, whether it be truth or a lye, although he ſwear or not ſwear,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118020:15"/> but Chriſt ſaith, Swear not at all, men muſt not do evill, that good may come of it, nor ſin that grace may abound. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, If the witneſs be reſolved to ſpeak falſly, and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate or Iudge put upon him an Oath, hee is the meanes to cauſe him to add ſin unto ſin: Now to prevent both ſwearing and lying by Witneſſes, obſerve what here follows, one wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall not riſe up againſt a man for any iniquity, or for any ſinne in any ſinne that he ſinneth, at the mouth of two Witneſſes, or at the mouth of three Witneſſes ſhall the matter be eſtabliſhed; if a falſe Witneſs riſe up againſt any man, to teſtifie againſt him that which is wrong, then both the men between whom the controverſie is, ſhall ſtand before the Lord, before the Prieſt and the Iudges, which ſhall bee in thoſe dayes, and the Judges ſhall make diligent inquiſition; and behold, if the Witneſs be a falſe Witneſs, and hath teſtified falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt his brother, then ſhall he do unto him as he had thought to have done unto his brother; ſo ſhalt thou put away evill from among you, and thoſe which remain ſhall hear and fear, and ſhall from henceforth commit no more ſuch evill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, and thine eye ſhall not pitty, but life ſhall go for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, foot for foot, <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.15, 16. You may ſee here was no command for witneſſes to ſwear, therefore the Rulers, Iudges, and Iuſtices, here is righteouſneſs and equity for you ro act by, according to that of God in your conſciences, and ſo ſhal you bring the lyar and the falſe Witneſs to juſtice, and prevent men for tranſgreſſing the Law of God, which is pure and good, by ſwearing, and ſo put away ſwearing out of the land, and do not compel men to ſwear, nor fine them that obey the commandment of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, by refuſing to ſweare, but lay your Sword of Iuſtice upon the evill doers, for whom it is appointed, and follow no longer the tradition of the Heathen, and do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, making the commandments of GOD of none effect; it is not good to reſpect mens perſons in judgement:</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118020:16"/>
            <p>And he ſet Judges in all the Land, throughout all the fenced cities of Judah, city by citie, and he ſaid to the Judges, Take heed what you do; for you judg not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in judgment; wherefore now let the feare of the Lord be upon you, take heed and do it, for there is no ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity with the Lord our God, nor reſpect of perſons, nor ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of gifts, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19; 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Babels Prophets are four hundred and fifty men, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of the Groves that fed at Jeſabels table four hundred, and but one, even one Prophet of Elijah that had bread and fleſh brought to him by Ravens, and he drank water of the brook, and cheriſht and walked in the ſtrength of the meat and cruſe of water 40 days, and 40 nights, which was brought him in the wilderneſs as he lay a ſleep under the juniper tree, and 400. of the Lords Prophets hid by fifty in a cave, and fed with bread and water, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 18.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If the Lord be God, follow him, if Baal be God, follow him ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 1. <hi>line</hi> 2 <hi>read</hi> out on. <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 17. <hi>r.</hi> lay, <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>l,</hi> 26. <hi>dele.</hi> of thoſe, <hi>l.</hi> 32 <hi>dele.</hi> of them. <hi>p,</hi> 8. <hi>l:</hi> 18. <hi>r.</hi> communion, <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 10, <hi>r. profit</hi> proſelyte, <hi>p:</hi> 14. <hi>l.</hi> 12 <hi>r. ſcornful</hi> ſenſual.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page l.</hi> 18. 5 <hi>li. dee</hi> in, <hi>p:</hi> 19. <hi>l.</hi> 7 <hi>r.</hi> Wirr <hi>Wire,</hi> p. 28. <hi>l.</hi> 8, <hi>r. Babels Pauls l.</hi> 20. <hi>r. one Prophet of the Lord Elijah, l.</hi> 12. <hi>r. brook</hi> Cherith.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:118020:16"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
